<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hjel2.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://hjel2.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-07T16:02:22+00:00</updated><id>https://hjel2.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Harry Langford. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Cambridge Computer Science applications</title><link href="https://hjel2.github.io/blog/2024/applying/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cambridge Computer Science applications"/><published>2024-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://hjel2.github.io/blog/2024/applying</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hjel2.github.io/blog/2024/applying/"><![CDATA[<p>This aims to provide general information about the application process: specifically highlighting that which is often miscommunicated.</p> <h2 id="what-do-i-have-to-do-to-get-an-offer">What do I have to do to get an offer?</h2> <p><strong>Work very hard, be very smart and know some programming.</strong></p> <p>These are the only things you <em>need</em>. The rest of your application serves only to validate intelligence and hard work. Any guide on what to do to get into Oxbridge isn’t a checklist: it’s a collection of things which would indicate to an academic that you are smart and work hard.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="what-you-have-to-do">What you have to do</h3> <p>These are the things everyone receiving an offer will have done.</p> <h4 id="do-well-at-school">Do well at school</h4> <p>Everyone who gets an offer works hard and is genuinely smart. You <em>need</em> to work hard at A Level, especially maths. The more, the better. Even work which is not directly related to computer science (i.e., Maths, Physics, Chemistry) is helpful and looks good on a personal statement. Doing past paper questions, competitions, getting good exam results are all important.</p> <h4 id="know-how-to-program">Know how to program</h4> <p>Knowing how to program will help a lot, even if it isn’t <em>technically</em> necessary. I’d strongly recommend learning how to program: knowing how to invent or implement simple algorithms or data structures and ‘think like a programmer’. I would not recommend overly familiarising yourself with libraries. Lots of interview questions are much easier if you know some basic programming.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="what-you-could-do">What you could do</h3> <p>Computer Science is very practical, so there is a lot you can do to demonstrate that you are smart: and which is best depends on you personally.</p> <h4 id="read-some-books">Read some books</h4> <p>This is less relevant than for other degrees. Here are my recommendations for computer science books (roughly in-order):</p> <ul> <li>Introduction to Algorithms</li> <li>Software and Security Engineering </li> </ul> <p>You can usually find any these online by searching the name with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">pdf</code> as a suffix.</p> <h4 id="do-some-cool-projects">Do some cool projects</h4> <p>If you can think of some projects to do, then do them! If I was an interviewer, this would be most impressive for me. Finding a sufficiently difficult and well-scoped project to do is challenging.</p> <h4 id="go-to-events">Go to events</h4> <p>If there are events which you can do, go for them! They can be very good.</p> <p>Some examples which come to mind are:</p> <ul> <li>game jams</li> <li>hackathons</li> <li>CTFs</li> <li>summer camps</li> </ul> <h4 id="learn-a-new-language">Learn a new language</h4> <p>Depth is <em>significantly</em> preferable to breadth: it’s far better to know how to program or to know one language inside out than know three at a surface-level. If you know how to program very well and are very confident in one language, then learning another strengthens your application.</p> <p>My recommendations for languages are in this order:</p> <ol> <li>a ‘simple’ language i.e. <a href="https://wiki.python.org/moin/IntroductoryBooks">Python</a></li> <li>an OOP language i.e. Java or C#</li> <li>an old language i.e. C++</li> <li>a difficult language i.e. <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/">Rust</a>, OCaml, Haskell</li> </ol> <p>It’s <em>much</em> better to know how to program than to learn different languages. Learning how to program will help at interview and A Level. Learning different languages will be confusing due to syntax differences.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="personal-statement">Personal Statement</h2> <p>Personal statements are difficult to write. Everyone has a lot of trouble with theirs.</p> <p>I would recommend writing a personal statement as follows:</p> <ol> <li>bulletpoint <em>everything</em></li> <li>arrange the bulletpoints into sections</li> <li>write paragraphs from those bulletpoints</li> <li><strong>iterate with competent people</strong></li> </ol> <p>Iterating with competent people is by far the most important. Choose a small group (1-2) of highly competent teachers to send your personal statement to and get feedback from. These teachers should know about either maths or computer science. Iterating with friends is useful: good friends care more; smarter friends generally give better feedback. Students are more willing to swap personal statements as the deadline approaches.</p> <h2 id="choosing-a-college">Choosing a College</h2> <p>This can feel daunting: don’t worry. The only ‘bad’ choice is an open application.</p> <p>Things to consider:</p> <ul> <li>accommodation</li> <li>proximity to town/CL</li> <li>‘looks’ and ‘feels’</li> <li>facilities</li> <li><a href="https://www.undergraduate.study.cam.ac.uk/apply/statistics">subject distribution</a> – how many other computer scientists there are and whether it’s STEM-centric or not etc</li> </ul> <p><strong>College choice does not meaningfully or predictably affect overall probability of an offer.</strong> Pooling exists to deal with oversubscribed colleges. College choice only affects probability of a pooled offer. There is also variety in quality of applicants between colleges.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="dont-get-filtered-by-ctmua">Don’t get filtered by CTMUA</h2> <p>After applying, but before the interview, you will have to sit a test called CTMUA. There are a <em>lot</em> of candidates and this is just designed to filter out a lot early on. The past questions can feel easy, but don’t underestimate it: <a href="https://www.physicsandmathstutor.com/admissions/tmua/">revise for it properly</a> and don’t get filtered.</p> <p>You should:</p> <ul> <li>read and understand the <a href="https://www.physicsandmathstutor.com/pdf-pages/?pdf=https%3A%2F%2Fpmt.physicsandmathstutor.com%2Fdownload%2FAdmissions%2FTMUA%2FTMUA%20Notes%20on%20Logic%20and%20Proof%202021.pdf">notes</a> and <a href="https://www.physicsandmathstutor.com/pdf-pages/?pdf=https%3A%2F%2Fpmt.physicsandmathstutor.com%2Fdownload%2FAdmissions%2FTMUA%2FTMUA%20Specification%202021.pdf">specification</a></li> <li>do all the past papers <em>without looking at solutions</em> – there aren’t many so don’t waste them</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="the-interview">The Interview</h2> <p>Colleges handle interviews separately and there is year-on-year variation. I therefore cannot give overly specific advice, but rather general themes which held across all or most interviews I’m aware of.</p> <h4 id="theres-a-lot-of-incorrect-information-about-interview-questions">There’s a lot of incorrect information about interview questions</h4> <p>Most practice interview material you can find online is <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/oxbridgeinterviewquestions/computer-science">unrealistic</a>. There’s a limited number of possible good computer science interview questions, so top universities don’t like publishing large repositories of them. </p> <p>The Cambridge interview process consists of a few multi-part questions. Questions are computer science or maths problems which usually are phrased using real-world examples to make them answerable using only maths: think ‘Alice has a box and a coin, Bob has a padlock’ rather than ‘Alice has a public key, a private key and a message she wants to send to Bob’.</p> <p>The first part of many questions easy and designed to verify that the candidate has understood the problem. The last part of a question is sometimes <em>very</em> difficult or materially unsolvable.</p> <p>Some colleges, but not many, will make one of the questions depend on something mentioned in your CV. Most will not. It’s possible, but very rare, to get a direct personal question i.e. ‘why are you better than other applicants’ is the worst I’ve heard.</p> <h4 id="check-if-your-college-uses-csat">Check if your college uses CSAT</h4> <p>Some colleges use CSAT: a written exam. Make sure you know whether your college requires CSAT. Colleges which use CSAT sometimes go through CSAT answers as part of the interview.</p> <h4 id="realistic-interview-preparation-resources">Realistic interview preparation resources</h4> <p>Here are some resources which I think are more realistic and useful.</p> <ul> <li>A Level maths: be familiar with all topics in A Level maths</li> <li><a href="https://openclimb.io/practice/#papers">CSAT</a></li> <li>Oxford has some <a href="https://www.cs.ox.ac.uk/admissions/undergraduate/how_to_apply/sample_interview_problem.html">example questions</a></li> <li><a href="https://www.maths.ox.ac.uk/study-here/undergraduate-study/maths-admissions-test/mat-past-papers">MAT</a> contains relevant questions</li> <li>simple <a href="https://stepdatabase.maths.org/">STEP questions</a> on relevant topics are useful </li> <li>old <a href="https://www.olympiad.org.uk/problems.html">BIO questions</a> and other ‘easier’ <a href="https://codeforces.com/">CP questions</a> are relevant (≤1200)</li> <li><strong>ask competent teachers</strong> for resources</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="guides"/><category term="cambridge"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A slightly formatted brain dump of everything I know about Cambridge applications]]></summary></entry></feed>